it's that time once again a card that
has the word enchantment on it is four
or more mana and mentions something
about base power and toughness has
recently been printed so you better
believe we're talking about Bellow again
the card in question is March of the
world Ooze from Aether drift a six minor
enchantment that says creatures you
control have base power and toughness 66
and are oozes in addition to their other
types and whenever an opponent casts a
spell if it's not their turn you create
a 33 green elephant creature token in
case you need a refresher Bellow bard of
the brambles is a three Mina 33 that
says during your turn each non-equipment
artifact and non Ora enchantment you
control with Mana value four or greater
is a 44 Elemental creature in addition
to its other types and has
indestructible haste and whenever this
creature deals combat damage to a player
draw a card for those that have seen my
previous video about Bellow let me know
in the comments down below what happens
when we have a March of the world who's
in Play and then cast Bellow what power
and toughness will March of the world
oze
have before we jump into the answer it's
important to understand exactly what
Bellow and March of the world ooze are
doing both March of the world oo's first
ability and Bellow's ability are both
types of continuous effects as per rule
6111 a continuous effect modifies
characteristics of objects modifies
control of objects or affects players or
the rules of the game for a fixed or
indefinite period the easy way to
remember this is if something changes
the printed information on a card that's
a continuous effect being applied to it
now seeing as we have two continuous
effects here and they're interacting
with each other that means we need to
look at my favorite page in the
comprehensive rules the page that
contains rule 613 interaction of
continuous effects that's right we're
talking about layers again but before
you click away know that I actually want
to focus and go into a specific rule on
layers that not too many people
cover okay here's the very basics of
layers you need to know there are seven
types of continuous effects copy effects
like clone control effects like mind
control text changing effects like
kit type changing effects like storm
tidle Leviathan color changing effects
like devoid effects that add or remove
abilities like humility and effects that
change or set Power and toughness like
giant growth when we have one or more of
these effects in play we apply them in
order of the layers list from top to
bottom let's take a look at Bellow and
March of the world ooze and see which
layers they impact if we go down the
layers list we can see we have an
interaction at layer four both Bellow
and World oo are attempting to change
types going further down the list we can
see that Bellow is adding abilities
that's on layer six and finally both
Bellow and World ooze are trying to set
Power and toughness that's layer
7B now that we know what effects we're
trying to apply here and what layer
they're on the next question is when we
get to a layer that has two or more
effects how do you know what order you
apply them in for example on layer 7B we
have Bellow trying to set creatures to
four fours and World ooze trying to set
things to be six sixes this is where we
need to learn about two things
dependencies and time stamps let's start
with the easier one first timestamps
basically whenever an object enters a
Zone it gets a time stamp time stamps
are effectively a marker showing the age
of something for example if we played
Bellow and then we played March of the
world ooze Bellow would have an older
Tim stamp than March of the world ooze
there are a couple of ways things can
get new timestamps if you flickered
Bellow from the previous example Bellow
would have re-entered the battlefield
entered a Zone and would get a new Tim
stamp there are a couple of other ways
that objects can get new time stamp
but that's for another video the
important thing to take away from this
is that continuous effects generated by
a static ability have the same Tim stamp
as the object that the static ability is
on one thing I see get brought up every
time I talk about Bellow is that does
Bellow's ability get a new timestamp
each turn no The Continuous effect Tim
stamp is tied to Bellow itself the only
time and ability would get a new Tim
stamp is if it was a triggered ability
so if Bell's ability said at the
beginning of your turn creatures you
control become blah blah blah that would
be a triggered ability and the ability
would get a new timestamp each time it
triggered so now that we know what time
stamps are the final thing to learn is
that we apply continuous effects on the
same layer in Tim stamp order oldest to
new
and before anyone asks if multiple
permanents enter the battlefield at the
same time starting with the active
player they choose the timestamp order
for their permanence and then you repeat
this process around the table in apnap
order okay now that we know about
timestamps we need to learn about
dependencies and this is the topic that
I really wanted to make clear as this
has tripped me up in the past when
looking at rulings now while we usually
apply Contin ous effects on the same
layer in time stamp order sometimes we
do it based on
dependencies a dependency is said to
take place when a later effect on the
same layer would impact the first or
more specifically an effect is said to
depend on another if a it's applied in
the same layer as the other effect B
applying the other would change the text
or the existence of the first first
effect what it applies to or what it
does to any of the things it applies to
and C neither effect is from a
characteristic defining ability or both
effects are from characteristic defining
abilities otherwise the effect is
considered to be independent of the
other effect if we look at March of the
world ooze we can see that it wants to
make creatures oozes in addition to
their other types and Bellow turns
things into creatures and these are
happening on the same layer layer four
so if we had March of the worldo in play
first then played Bellow if we followed
the time stamp system we would give All
Creatures the Ooze type and then Bellow
would make artifacts and enchantments
creatures meaning the creatures that
Bellow animated wouldn't also be oozers
so here we can see that Bell's ability
directly impacts what March of the world
ooze will be applying Y 2 in other words
Marge of the world ooze depends on
Bellow's effect to be applied first so
that it can make all creatures into ooes
while this isn't a massive deal for this
example it's good to be aware of
dependencies for other
interactions so back to the original
question what happens when we have a
March of the world ooze in play and then
cast Bellow as discussed we know that
effect here come into play at layers 4 6
and 7B so we'll run down the list and
apply them at layer four we know that
March of the world ooze is dependent on
Bellows effect so we'll apply Bellow's
effect first making each non-equipment
artifact and non-or enchantment you
control with Mana value four or greater
an elemental creature in addition to its
other types we'll then apply March of
the world ooze and make them oozes as
well
going down the list we get to layer six
and give each a non-equipment artifact
and non Ora enchantment with Mana value
four or greater indestructible haste and
whenever this creature deals combat
damage to a player draw a card we then
come to layer 7B where we're setting
power and
toughness here because neither ooze or
Bellow is dependent on each other as
they all apply to the same thing without
changing what the other would apply to
we simply apply these effects effects in
time stamp order so because March of the
world ooze was in play first we apply
that ability first making All Creatures
six
sixes then we apply Bellow because they
have the newest Tim stamp and turn all
the non-equipment artifact and non Ora
enchantment creatures into four fours so
there's your answer March of the world
ooze will be a 44 but all other non
artifact non- enchantment creatures will
six
sixes now bonus question what happens if
we now play
humility so that's what happens with
Bellow and the world ooze if you learned
something be sure to like the video and
subscribe because if you don't Bell will
summon elrazi to moranda and you'll
never find out who this is thanks for
watching and I'll see you in the next
one